Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - VARNHAGEN VON ENSE, KARL AUGUST LUDWIG PHILIPP
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1830 Mar 12 (Box 17, Folder 740)
      Weimarischen Lexikon."
      Published in Carl F. Schreiber's Sieben
      Briefe Varnhagens von Ense an Johann
      Peter Eckermann, in Journal of
      English and Germanic philology,
      v. 21, July, 1922.
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1832 Sep 17 (Box 17, Folder 741)
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1836 May 20 (Box 17, Folder 742)
      3 p.; 13 x 22 cm.
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1836 Jun 18 (Box 17, Folder 743)
      2 p.; 13 x 22 cm.
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1838 May 7 (Box 17, Folder 744)
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1839 Mar 26 (Box 17, Folder 745)
    - ALS: Berlin, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1842 Mar 26 (Box 17, Folder 746)
  - VISCHER, FRIEDRICH THEODOR, 1807-1887
    - 11 ALS: Tübingen, to Arnold Ruge, 1838-1842 (Box 17, Folder 747)
      21 p.; 20-22 cm.
      January 16, 1838 to July 8, 1842.
      Chiefly concerning contributions by
      Vischer to the Hallesche Jahrbücher
      für Kunst und Wissenschaft and
      Deutscher Musenalmanach of which
      Ruge was co-editor.
      The letters of Jan. 16 and Dec. 10,
      1838 include references to works on
      Published by Adolph B. Benson in
      Philological quarterly, v. 3.,
      p. 32-47.
      With: ALS: Tübingen, to Lauppische
      Buchhandlung in Leipzig, 1842 Apr 5
      pertaining to the Collier edition of
      Shakespeare's works.
  - VOGEL, W.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Johann Karl Wilhelm Voigt, 1842 Sep 16 (Box 17, Folder 748)
  - VOIGT, FRAU AMALIE HENRIETTE CAROLINE (LUDECUS) VON
    Dates: 1776-1840
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Theuerster Freund", 1821 Sep 21 (Box 17, Folder 749)
      Letter is mounted.
  - VOIGT, CHRISTIAN GOTTLOB VON, 1744-1819
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Verehrtester Freund", 1817 Nov 4 (Box 17, Folder 750)
  - VOIGT, JOHANN HEINRICH VON, 1751-1823
    - ALS: Jena, to Prorector Justus Christian Loder, 1799 Mar 17 (Box 17, Folder 751)
  - VOSS, JOHANN HEINRICH, 1779-1822
    - ALS: Weimar, to Heinrich Karl Abraham Eichstädt?, [1805?] (Box 17, Folder 752)
  - VULPIUS, CHRISTIAN AUGUST, 1762-1827
    - ALS: Weimar, to Freiherr Joseph von Hammer-Purgstall, 1820 Jan 4 (Box 17, Folder 753)
      Signed: D. Vulpius, Rath u
      Oberbibliothekar.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Karl Gottfried Theodor Winkler, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 754)
      Date is cut away.
  - WAGNER, GOTTLOB HEINRICH ADOLF, 1774-1835
    - ALS: Leipzig, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1826 Jun 30 (Box 18, Folder 755)
      2 p.; 12 x 21 cm.
  - WALCH, CHRISTIANE F. W. (HERZLIEB) MINNA, 1789-1865
    Full name: Frau Christiane Friederike
    Wilhelmine (Herzlieb) Minna Walch
    - ALS: Prittag near Züllichau, to Friedrich Johannes Fromann?, 1830 Jun 30 (Box 18, Folder 756)
    - AL (fragment): Jena, to Christiane Selig, 1808 Feb 10 (Box 18, Folder 757)
      The complete letter is printed in Karl
      Theodor Gaedertz, Goethes Minchen,
      auf Grund ungedruckter Briefe, 1887,
      p. 46-60.
  - WALLENSTEIN, ALBRECHT W. E. VON, 1583-1634
    Full name: Albrecht Wenzel Eusebius
    von Wallenstein, Herzog von Friedland
    Document, signed, Halberstad. 1629 Dec 3
    - 1 l.; 49 x 33 cm. Signed: "Wir Albrecht von Gottes gnaden Hertzog zue Mechelburg ..." Patent, issued by Wallenstein as Duke Albrecht of Mecklenburg, regulating the maintenance of Mecklenburg officers and troops while in the territory of Prince Christian von Anhalt. Text written in chancellary style.
    - See: Oversize Box 19, folder 832
  - WEBER, BERNHARD ANSELM, 1766-1821
    - ALS: Berlin, to Wiedebein, 1819 Jun 4 (Box 18, Folder 758)
      Wiedebein was an orchestra conductor
      at Braunschweig.
      Discusses the overture to Weber's
      Wilhelm Tell.
  - WEIL, HANS HARTMUT
    - Some reflections on the use and usefulness of the concepts "höfisch" and "antihöfisch" (Box 18, Folder 759)
      Typescript (carbon), 21 l.; 36 cm.
      Appendix to "Man's role in German
      Baroque literature," Cambridge, 1952.
      Footnotes include bibliography.
      With: TLS: Kingston, Ontario, to
      Prof. von Faber du Faur, Jan. 5,
      1953; 2 p.; 28 cm.; concerning
      the manuscript above.
  - WEYLAND, PHILIPP CHRISTIAN, 1766-1843
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Hochverehrter Herr Oberhofmarschall", 1836 Aug 8 (Box 18, Folder 760)
      Weyland was secretary to Karl August,
      duke of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach.
  - WHEWELL, WILLIAM, 1794-1866
    - ALS: Cambridge, England, to Hermann Kindt, 1863 Oct 19 (Box 18, Folder 761)
      Letterhead: Trinity Lodge, Cambridge.
      Discusses Whewell's English translation
      of Goethe's Hermann und Dorothea.
  - WIELAND, CHRISTOPH MARTIN, 1733-1813
    - ALS: Weimar, to Johannes Falk, 1808 Apr 22 (Box 18, Folder 762)
      3 p.; 10 x 20 cm.
      Criticism of the fourth issue, April
      1808, of the periodical "Phoebus,"
      ed. by Heinrich von Kleist and Adam
      Heinrich Müller; directed
      specifically against the latter.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Philipp Christoph Kayser, bey Herrn Pfarrer Lavater, Zürich, 1776 Sep 30 (Box 18, Folder 763)
    - Autograph contract with Carl Ludolf Hoffmann, Weimar, 1776 Mar 27 (Box 18, Folder 764)
      With 3 official red seals.
      Contract between editor and publisher
      for the 1776-1777 issues of "Der
      Teutsche Merkur."
    - Autograph receipt, signed [fragment], Weimar, 1787 Sep (Box 18, Folder 765)
      Upper portion of sheet containing list
      of items received, torn off.
      Below Wieland's signature is written a
      bill for firewood, followed by
      signature A. A. Cannebich[?]
  - WIELAND, LUDWIG FRIEDRICH AUGUST, 1777-1819
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Wohlgebohrner Herr", [1817?] May 14 (Box 18, Folder 766)
      Ludwig Wieland was the eldest son of
      Christoph Martin Wieland.
      A request for two copies of his edition
      of his father's letters.
  - WILLEMER, MARIANNE (JUNG) VON, 1784-1860
    - ALS: Frankfurt, to Alexandre Bernus, 1855 Dec 30 (Box 18, Folder 767)
      3 p.; 21 cm.
      With envelope, postmarked Jan. 3, 1856,
      and red seal.
  - WILSON, HENRY SCHÜTZ
    - ALS: Hanover Square W., [London], to the editor of the New Review, 1889 Oct 7 (Box 18, Folder 768)
      Offering an article on Goethe
      anecdotes. The recipient, under date
      of the 11th, has written "Unable."
      Apparently the article appeared later
      in the Athenaeum 1889 under the
      title: Anecdote of Goethe.
  - WINTER, WILLIAM, 1836-1917
    - Henry Irving as Mephistopheles, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 769)
      11 l.; various lengths: 20 x 25 -
      20 x 48 cm.
      At head of title, the ms. note: Drama
      (First article).
      Pencil note on verso of last leaf:
      Original ms. of Essay of mine on
      Henry Irving as Mephistopheles.
      Written for the New York Tribune.
      Winter did not republish it in his
      three vols. series of Shadows of the
      stage.
    - Autograph note, signed, on p. l. of printed "Speech of Henry Irving, before the Goethe Society, at the Madison Square Theatre, New York, March 15, 1888", n.d. (Box 18, Folder 770)
      The printed text of the speech
      comprises 10 p.
      Text of note: "This MS[!] was used by
      Henry Irving in the delivery of this
      speech, & subsequently was given to
      me by him ... Parke Godwin presided
      & spoke & a speech was made by George
      William Curtis."
  - WOLF, FRIEDRICH AUGUST, 1759-1824
    - Autograph certificate, signed, Halle, 1803 May 1 (Box 18, Folder 771)
      Certifying that Student Ziehe of Berlin
      has attended Wolf's lectures on the
      Encyclopädie der philologischen
      Wissenschaften.
      For Goethe's relation with Wolf see
      Bernays, Michael: Briefwechsel
      zwischen Goethe und F.A. Wolf.
  - WOLFF, ANNA AMALIA CHRISTIANE (MALCOLMI), 1783-1851
    - ALS: Berlin, to "Lieber Freund", 1834 Jul 29 (Box 18, Folder 772)
      The author was a celebrated actress,
      the wife of the actor Pius Alexander
      Wolff, both at the Weimar theatre.
  - WOLFF, PIUS ALEXANDER, 1782-1828
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Ew. Hochedelgebohren!", 1804 Sep 1 (Box 18, Folder 773)
      Asking assistance in procuring a copy
      of A tale of mystery; a melo-drama,
      by Thomas Holcroft, London, 1802.
    - ALS, to Herrn Oberhofgerichtsrath Clümmer, Leipzig, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 774)
      Wolff promises to inform Clümmer what
      the following week's repertoire will
      be, after he has had a conference
      with Genast.
  - WOLZOGEN, CAROLINE (VON LENGEFELD) VON, 1763-1847
    - ALS: Jena, to Frau Caroline Riemer, 1841 Jan 15 (Box 18, Folder 775)
      With envelope and red personal seal
      attached.
      Signed: C. Wolzogen.
    - ALS, to Karl Hermann Scheidler, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 776)
      Concerning an exchange of Goethe
      mementoes between Frau von Wolzogen
      and Scheidler.
    - ALS, to Wilhelm von Wolzogen?, 1787 Apr 19 (Box 18, Folder 777)
      8 p.; 13 x 18 cm.
      Karoline von Wolzogen was Schiller's
      sister-in-law and the author of the
      novel "Agnes von Lilien" which was at
      one time ascribed to Goethe.
  - WORDSWORTH, WILLIAM, 1770-1850
    - ALS: Rydal Mount, to John Hills, 1840 Feb 20 (Box 18, Folder 778)
      Thanking Hills for his gift of a copy
      of his translation of Goethe's Faust,
      and for an appreciative note in his
      commentary.
  - WÜNSCH, ALBERT
    - 9 items bound together, 1882-84 (Box 18, Folder 779)
      1) Die verwandelten Weiber; oder, Der
      Teufel ist los. Lustspiel in 3
      Aufzügen, 1882.
      AMs, signed, 87 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Title from label on cover.
      Signed: Albert Wünsch. Orderan den
      13ten Juli 1882.
      Based on Christian Felix Weisse's opera
      of the same title, which was set to
      music by Johann Adam Hiller.
      2) Der Geiger und sein Liebchen, n.d.
      AMs, 3 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Poem apparently spoken to accompany a
      pantomime.
      Not in Albert Wünsch's handwriting.
      Incomplete? The rhyme would indicate
      that a portion is wanting between
      p.[2] and [3].
      3) Hoffnung, Liebe, Glaube, n.d.
      Divided in 1.-3. Bild: 1. Hoffnung
      2. Liebe; 3. Hoffnung, Glaube, Liebe.
      Poem in five verses.
      In the same handwriting as that of the
      second version of Goethe's Der
      Fischer, and of the poem "Nach meiner
      Meinung ganz egal", in the same
      volume.
      4) Jetzt geths[!] los! 48, n.d.
      AMs, 5 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      A poem in four verses.
      "48" in title may mean "1848".
      5) Lied und Liebe. (Lebendes Bild 2
      Tableaux), n.d.
      A poem in nine verses.
      6) Nach meiner Meinung ganz egal, n.d.
      A poem in six verses; the first in a
      different handwriting from the rest,
      which is that of the transcriber of
      the second version of Goethe's Der
      Fischer, in the same volume.
      7) Die Wacht am Rhein Rhein.
      (Lebentes[!] Bild in 2 Tablaux),
      Lengefeld, 1884 Jun 17.
      AMs, 2 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      First line: Ein einsam Bild auf hoher
      Warte.
      Not M. Schneckenburger's famous poem
      (Es braust ein Ruf wie Donnerhall).
      8) Müller, Karl. Des Fischers letzter
      Fang, n.d.
      AMs, signed, 4 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Holograph copy of Goethe's Poem "Der
      Fischer."
      In the same handwriting as "Der Geiger
      und sein Liebchen" in the same
      Transcription full of errors and
      dialect inflections; the verse before
      the last is omitted and supplied, in
      pencil in a different handwriting,
      following Müller's signature.
      Divided in 1.-2. Bild.
      On slip inserted at front, in G.
      Ehrhardt's handwriting: "Goethes ...
      Ballade "Der Fischer" wurde von dem
      Marionettentheaterbesitzer und
      Spieler Apel unter der Bezeichnung
      "Des Fischers letzter Fang" noch
      zwischen 1880 u. 1890 nach den
      Aufführungen der Puppenstücke ... als
      persönliches Nachspiel (lebendes
      Bild) aufgeführt."
      9) Another holograph copy, in a different
      handwriting, of the same poem under
      title: Des Fischers letzter Fang, n.d.
      AMs, 2 p.; 21 x 17 cm., bound
      following the above.
  - ZAHN, WILHELM JOHANN KARL, 1800-1871
    - ALS, to Baron von Bockelberg, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 780)
  - ZELTER, CARL FRIEDRICH, 1758-1832
    - ALS: Berlin, to "Verehrter Herr College", 1830 Mar 21 (Box 18, Folder 781)
      Thanking for several recent articles
      on Goethe.
      Zelter is happy to perceive that the
      younger generation is active in its
      researches on Goethe.
  - ZWIERLEIN, CARL JULIUS WILHELM
    - ALS, to Herrn Baumann, 1844 Apr 11 (Box 18, Folder 782)
      Zwierlein was
      "Hofmarschallamtssecretär" at the
      court of the Duke of Saxe-Weimar-
      Eisenach; Baumann, "Hofgärtner" at
  - UNIDENTIFIED AUTHORS
    - A Monsieur le Major Stith, Conseil des États Unis d'Amérique a Tunis, 1823 Jul 4 (Box 18, Folder 783)
      Autograph poem, signed J.E.H.
      With a pressed flower, now in
    - Autograph list of eight books and their prices, in an unidentified hand (Box 18, Folder 784)
      Watermark: Carl August, Grossherzog
      von Sachsen Weimar Eisenach, 1757-
      1828, with his portrait within the
      circle formed by the inscription.
    - Autograph note: "Feb.1-4. ist vom Staats Minister v. Göthe den 1 Apr. mitgetheilt worden.", n.d (Box 18, Folder 785)
      1 p.; 8 x 13 cm.
      In an unidentified hand.
    - Collection of maxims by various German authors (Box 18, Folder 786)
      4 p., 2 l. various sizes.
      In an unidentified handwriting.
      The two leaves each have a maxim
      by Schiller in calligraphic
      writing, apparently done by
      the same hand; one within the
      ornamental border in lavender,
      the other on double sheet with
      floral decoration within blind
      embossed ornamental border.
      Other maxims by Löwen, Jean Paul,
      Hagedorn, Schiller, Goethe,
      Göckingk, Voss, Pfeffel, Uz,
      Matthison, and others.
    - Innere Zusammenhänge in Goethes Faust, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 787)
      53 l.; 29 x 23 cm.
      Typescript (Original)
    - Le Juif Errant. Extraits de l'annuaire de la bibliothèque royale de Belgique, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 788)
      AMs, 46 p.; 21 x 28 cm.
      Note on p. 1: "Annuaire de la
      Bibliothèque de Belgique,
      par le conservateur Baron de
      Reiffenberg, chevalier etc.
      Troisième année. Bruxelles et
      Leipzig. C. Muquardt 1842 ...
      p.298, [i.e. 198]-206."
      Grey board cover.
      "Soergel nicht zugänglich
      gewesen." Ehrhardt's catalogue
      note no. 3880.
    - M. Goethe, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 789)
      4 p.; 28 x 23 cm.
      Autograph biographical sketch.
      In upper right hand corner:
      Biographie des Contemporains.
      Clippings from unidentified
      newspapers or periodicals are
      pasted in various places as part
      of the text.
    - Zauber Buch Magia Naturalis et Innaturalis. n.d.
      - 129 unnumb. l. of col. illus., with t.p. in ms.; 21 x 14 cm. The illustrations consist of a blue flower, playing card (seven of spades), cabbalistic symbols, devil's head and a coat-of-arms repeated over and over in this order. Through cutting edges of leaves, six divisions are formed which enable the user to find readily the same picture. Formerly owned by Carl Engel. - Ehrhardt's catalogue note no. 577.
      - See: Bound Volumes, folder 830
- Bound Volumes, 1689-195-?; 4.5; (41 volumes)
  Volumes filed here are otherwise fully described
  in the register under the appropriate name entries.
  - Achard, Marcel, 1899-1974
    - I know my love. A comedy in three acts, adapted by N. S. Behrman, [195-?] (Box Vol, Folder 790)
  - Agrippa von Nettesheim, Heinrich Cornelius
    - La clavicule magique et cabalistique du Roy Salomon, avec les pentacules talismns, invocations, conjurations des esprits célestes, 1732 (Box Vol, Folder 791)
  - Binckes, Henry Ashbey
    - Faust, an opera by Henry Ashbey Binckes, London, 1867 (Box Vol, Folder 792)
  - Clavicula Salomonis
    - Clavicula Salomonis expurgate prit exrat im Vaticano assumta. Bibliotheca Aeldebergensi: Der König Salomon spricht zu seinem Sohn Rabeam, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 793)
  - Eschenburg, Johann Joachim, 1743-1820
    - Notes to his Archäologie der Literatur und Kunst ... Berlin und Stettin, F. Nikolai, 1787 (Box Vol, Folder 794)
    - Notes to his Entwurf einer Theorie und Literatur der schönen Wissenschaften. Zur Grundlage bei Vorlesungen ... neue, umgearb. Ausgabe ... Berlin und Stettin, F. Nikolai, 1789. (Box Vol, Folder 795a)
    - Notes to his Entwurf einer Theorie und Literatur der schönen Wissenschaften. Zur Grundlage bei Vorlesungen ... neue, umgearb. Ausgabe ... Berlin und Stettin, F. Nikolai, 1789. (Box Vol, Folder 795b)
    - Notes to his Entwurf einer Theorie und Literatur der schönen Wissenschaften. Zur Grundlage bei Vorlesungen ... neue, umgearb. Ausgabe ... Berlin und Stettin, F. Nikolai, 1789. (Box Vol, Folder 795c)
    - Notes to his Entwurf einer Theorie und Literatur der schönen Wissenschaften. Zur Grundlage bei Vorlesungen ... neue, umgearb. Ausgabe ... Berlin und Stettin, F. Nikolai, 1789. (Box Vol, Folder 795)
    - Notes to his II. Kurze Uebersicht der klassischen Schriftsteller des griechischen und römischen Alterthums (Box Vol, Folder 796)
  - Faust (attributed author)
    - D. Johann Fausts Miracul- und Wunder- Buch, der Höllen-Zwang genannt. Mit Characteren, Pentaculn und Sigillen, in XII. Theilen (Box Vol, Folder 797)
    - Der heimliche und unerforschliche Doctor Faustens, Höllen-Zwang genant. Gedruckt zu Lion, den 14. April, Anno 1407, Leipzig, 1727 Jun 18 (Box Vol, Folder 798)
  - Faust (Puppet-play)
    - Doktor Faust. Schauspiel in 4 Akten, 1864 (Box Vol, Folder 799)
    - Dr. Faust; oder Der Höllentriumph. Lustspiel in 4 Akten von Pirrinet, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 800)
    - Dr. Faust, Porschdorf, 1894 Sep 17 (Box Vol, Folder 801)
    - 2. Theil Faust. Christoph Wagner früher Famulus bei Faust. Puppenspiel in 6 Akten, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 802)
    - Dr. Faust. Lustspiel in 4 Akten, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 803)
    - Doctor Faust. Lustspiel in 4 Aufzügen, 1900 May 28 (Box Vol, Folder 804)
  - Goebel, Julius, 1857-1931
    - Papers on Goethe, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 805)
  - Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832
    - Faust; a tragedy. First part translated into English verse by Jonathan Birch. 3 vols., n.d.
      - Volume 1 (Box Vol, Folder 806a)
      - Volume 2 (Box Vol, Folder 806b)
      - Volume 3 (Box Vol, Folder 806c)
    - Faust; a tragedy in two parts. Second part translated into English verse by Jonathan Birch (Box Vol, Folder 807)
    - Faust, tragedy. By J. W. von Goethe. Translated in the original metres by Bayard Taylor. 1. and 2. parts, 1869 May 15 (Box Vol, Folder 808)
    - Der Raub der Helena. Scenen aus dem zweiten Theile des "Faust" von Göthe in 2 Aufzügen, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 809)
    - Faust. Dramatisches Gedicht von Goethe, in 6 Aufzügen, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 810)
    - The Sorrows of Werter; a German story, [1785?] (Box Vol, Folder 811)
    - Topkbato-Tacco. Russian translation by Taskin of Torquato Tasso, 1868 (Box Vol, Folder 812)
  - Autograph letters to Johann Hoffmann
    - 102 ALS to Johann Hoffmann from colleagues, students, and friends, 1689-1718 (Box Vol, Folder 813)
  - Kauffmann, Julie von
    - Autograph album containing 11 entries by teachers and friends of Julie von Kauffmann, 1866 (Box Vol, Folder 814)
  - Kolff, Jacob van Santen, 1848-1896
    - Der Faust-Ouverture Werden und Wachsen (Box Vol, Folder 815)
  - Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801
    - Sammlung von Gedanken zu einem allgemeinen Organon; oder, einmahl eins des Menschen, 1782 Nov 15 (Box Vol, Folder 816)
    - Das menschliche Herz. Sechs [i.e. Drei] Gesaenge, 1789 (Box Vol, Folder 817)
    - Lord Chatam, oder Pitts Büste Commentiert, für Heinrich Lipps, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 818)
    - Vermischte physiognomische Regeln. Manuscript für Freünde, mit einigen characterischen Linien. Erstes Hundert. Zum Bessten der Armen, 1789 (Box Vol, Folder 819)
    - Stufen, 1-3. 3 vols., n.d.
      - Volume 1 (Box Vol, Folder 820a)
      - Volume 2 (Box Vol, Folder 820b)
      - Volume 3 (Box Vol, Folder 820c)
  - Ludwig, Otto, 1813-1865
    - Zwischen Himmel und Erde (Box Vol, Folder 821)
  - Motley, John Lothrop, 1814-1877
    - Commonplace-book, [1838?] (Box Vol, Folder 822)
  - Penny, George B.
    - Schiller's ballads discussed as ballads and as poems. Compared with Goethe's ballads, etc. Sketch of the ballad, 1884 (Box Vol, Folder 823)
  - Post, Charlotte
    - Autograph cook-book, 1822 Jun 28 (Box Vol, Folder 824)
  - Reinbold, Adelheid, 1800-1839
    - Masaniello, Eine Julywoche des Jahres 1647. Dramatische Novelle, nach Quellen bearbeitet von Wilhelm Hof [pseud.], n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 825)
    - Saul, Trauerspiel in fünf Aufzügen, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 826)
  - Roertgen, William Francis
    - The literary reviews of the Frankfurter gelehrte Anzeigen 1772- 1790, [Berkeley], [1947] (Box Vol, Folder 827)
  - Schmidt, Clemens Gottlob
    - Das Buch "Hiob" erläutert von: Prof. O. D. Tuch, 1847-48 (Box Vol, Folder 828)
  - Speck, William Alfred, 1864-1928
    - Autograph album, 1879-80 (Box Vol, Folder 829)
  - Unidentified authors
    - Zauber Buch Magia Naturalis et Innaturalis, n.d. (Box Vol, Folder 830)
- Additions Since 2000, 1812-1830; 0.2; (1 box)
  - LS: Jena, to Johann Wolfgang Döbereiner, 1812 Mar 12 (Box 20, Folder 833)
    Letter written by Goethe's secretary
    Johann August Friedrich John and
    signed by Goethe,
    Printed in Weimar Ausgabe, Bd. XXII,
    Nr. 6273.
    Acc #: 19991115-e
  - LS: Weimar, to Johann Wolfgang Döbereiner, 1830 Jan 20 (Box 20, Folder 834)
    1 p.; 27 x 21 cm.
    Letter written in an unidentified
    hand and signed by Goethe.
    Printed in Weimar Ausgabe, Bd. XLVI,
    Nr. 205.
    Acc #: 19991115-f
  - Album containing pressed leaves and photographs, 1887-1914 (Box 20, Folder 835)
    17 leaves; 33 x 24 cm.
    Compiled and annotated by Karl Berg.
    Acc #: 13718
  - Katalog der Faust-Bücherei, Bilder- und Skulpturen-Sammlung, 1899, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 836-837)
    2 v.
    Handwritten inventory of George Wilhelm Heinrich Ehrhardt's Faust collection.
    Title from front cover of volume II: "Dr. Faust: Sage und Dichtung in der Bildkunst".
    Acc #: 26171
- Oversize, 2; (1 box)
  Oversize contains oversize material from
  the Box and Folder List and is arranged in a parallel
  arrangement.
  - BOX AND FOLDER LIST
    - Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832
      - Was man erfindet, thut man mit Liebe, Weimar, 1813 Dec 29 (Box 19, Folder 831)
      - Es ist dafür gesorgt dass die Bäume nicht in den Himmel wachsen, Weimar, 1814 Jan 17 (Box 19, Folder 831a)
    - Muller, Waltraud
      - Goethe. 12 poems, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 831b)
    - Wallenstein, Albrecht W. E. von, 1583-1634
      - Document, signed, Halberstad, 1629 Dec 3 (Box 19, Folder 832)